All right.
So welcome to our last lecture for 6UMB.
欢迎来到我们61B的最后一堂课
So let's kind of take a brief look at how we went through 6UMB over this past six months, four months?
让我们简单回顾一下过去四个月里我们是如何学习61B的？
It's only been four months.
才四个月
So just 14 weeks ago, we were here.
所以就在14周前  我们还在这里
We were just writing our first Hello World in Java.
我们刚用Java写了第一个Hello World程序
And then over the course of those first few weeks, we started learning a bit of how Java worked.
然后在接下来的几周里  我们开始学习一些Java的工作原理
We talked about how objects were created in Java, object-oriented programming.
我们讨论了如何在Java中创建对象  也就是面向对象编程
Unlike Python, Java is the statically typed language where every single variable needs to have a specific type and a specific object class.
与Python不同  Java是一种静态类型语言  每个变量都需要具有特定的类型和特定的对象类
You have these interfaces.
它有接口
You have classes, class inheritance, all sorts of things like that.
它有类、类继承等等
Programmers, we try to ensure that we have things as abstracted away as possible.
作为程序员  我们尽量确保将事物尽可能地抽象化
We don't want to think about all the complex details about how an ArrayList works when all we need is really a List class.
当我们只需要一个List类时  我们不想考虑ArrayList如何工作的复杂细节
So we want to distinguish between when we're the user of a class and when we're actually building the class itself.
我们要区分什么时候我们是类的使用者  什么时候我们是类本身的构建者
And we want those to be two separate people so we don't have to worry about how the other person behaved.
我们希望这两者是不同的角色  这样我们就不必担心对方的行为
We talked about dynamic versus static typing, how in Java, because of its statically typed language format,
我们讨论了动态类型和静态类型的区别  在Java中  由于它是静态类型语言格式
since every variable needs a type, you can also define its type based on a superclass of what its actual type is.
因为每个变量都需要一个类型  所以你也可以根据其实际类型的超类来定义它的类型
And you can still write code that ends up having that works.
并且你仍然可以编写最终有效的代码
You might have some various type checks in compile time, which are different from the checks that you'll see during actual runtime.
你可能会在编译时进行一些类型检查  这与你在实际运行时看到的检查不同
We talked a bit about how generics work.
我们还讨论了泛型的原理
So in Java, since everything needs to have a particular type, you can't just do arbitrary type objects.
所以在Java中  由于每样东西都需要有一个特定的类型  所以你不能仅仅使用任意类型的对象
So you need to specify exactly, instead of it just being an arbitrary list, you need to specify it's a list of integers or a list of dogs or a list of something else.
你需要准确地指定  而不是仅仅是一个任意的列表  你需要指定它是一个整数列表、一个狗的列表或其他什么的列表
We talked a bit about how arrays are actually just sequences of consecutive memory addresses.
我们稍微讨论了一下数组实际上是如何连续内存地址的序列
They're much faster to use than lists, but they can't be extended as a result.
它们的使用速度比列表快得多  但结果是它们不能被扩展
And that got us into some discussion on how there might be some trade-offs between certain approaches.
这让我们讨论了一些关于某些方法之间可能存在一些权衡的问题
We talked very briefly about how certain integers are represented, a lot about how Java ends up working under the hood.
我们简要地讨论了某些整数是如何表示的  以及Java最终是如何在底层工作的
We talked a lot about objects, default methods, iterators, things like that.
我们讨论了很多关于对象、默认方法、迭代器之类的东西
After we finished that, we went into details on collections.
在完成这些之后  我们详细讨论了集合
We talked a bit about a few of these specific data structures that we use a lot.
我们讨论了一些我们经常使用的数据结构
So collections are very common data structures which are designed to store a set of things or a list of things.
因此  集合是非常常见的数据结构  旨在存储一组东西或一个东西列表
So we had maps, lists.
所以我们有映射、列表
DQs, and that was our project one, getting us to make an actual DEC class.
Deque  那是我们的第一个项目  让我们制作一个实际的 DEC 类
We went into a bit of detail about the math behind actually what we're doing.
我们详细讨论了我们实际工作背后的数学原理
We talked a lot about asymptotic analysis, O bounds, omega bounds, theta bounds, and how those are different from worst case, average case, best case operations.
我们讨论了很多关于渐近分析、O界限、Ω界限、Θ界限  以及它们与最坏情况、平均情况、最佳情况操作的不同之处
And we saw throughout the semester a lot of different approaches in how certain bounds might have different use cases.
在整个学期中  我们看到了很多不同的方法  来处理某些情况下界限可能有不同用例的情况
For example, when you're looking at an array list, you're really looking at the average case runtime when you're looking at the amortized bound.
例如  当你查看数组列表时  你实际上是在查看摊销界限时的平均情况运行时间
Because an array list, it's still slowest worst case theta n time.
因为数组列表  它仍然是最慢的最坏情况 Θ(N) 时间
But that happens so infrequently that we can actually get theta 1 amortized time.
但这种情况很少发生  所以我们实际上可以得到 Θ(1) 摊销时间
Quick Start was another big example where we saw that, on average, in a random case, you're generally going to get n log n time.
快速排序是另一个重要的例子  我们看到  平均而言  在随机情况下  你通常会得到 N log N 的时间
But on those very, very unlucky cases, you end up getting n squared run time.
但在那些非常非常不幸运的情况下  你最终会得到 N² 的运行时间
We did try to look at some code and try and figure out the actual runtime.
我们确实尝试查看了一些代码  并试图找出实际的运行时间
But it tends to be quite difficult to do that.
但这往往很难做到
It uses a lot more math than in 61A, for example, you might see.
它使用的数学知识比 61A 课程中多很多  例如  你可能会看到
But comparable math to how you might see in CS70 or CS170.
但与 CS70 或 CS170 中看到的数学知识相当
And we also use this specifically when looking at ArrayList to show that when you do this multiplicative resizing,
我们还专门在研究 ArrayList 时使用了这一点  以表明当你进行这种乘法扩容时
those resizes are so rare that you get theta 1 amortized time.
这些扩容非常少见  以至于你得到了 Θ(1) 的摊销时间
But when you do additive resizing, you end up getting theta n average runtime.
但是当你进行加法扩容时  最终会得到 Θ(n) 的平均运行时间
Here's kind of a list of all the data structures that we looked at throughout this course.
以下是我们在本课程中所学到的所有数据结构的列表
We had sets, maps, priority queues, lists, disjoint sets, graphs.
我们有集合、映射、优先队列、列表、不相交集、图
And we also looked at a lot of different approaches on how to implement them.
我们还研究了许多不同的实现方法
We saw that, for example, we could implement a priority queue with a balanced tree or with a heap.
例如  我们看到可以使用平衡树或堆来实现优先队列
We also saw we could implement it with an ordered linked list, but that was way, way slower.
我们还看到可以使用有序链表来实现它  但这要慢得多
So we generally don't do that.
所以我们一般不这样做
No.
So here's all the blue ones are the ones that we found that were efficient enough that we could actually use it in real life.
这里所有蓝色的都是我们发现效率足够高  可以在现实生活中实际使用的
The red ones are the ones which are just so slow that they're not really useful, not practical for our purposes.
红色的那些太慢了  以至于它们不是很有用  对我们的目的来说不实用
So we had these array-based data structures versus linked list data structures.
我们有这些基于数组的数据结构和基于链表的数据结构
Array lists, they're really good at accessing an arbitrary point in the item.
数组列表非常擅长访问项目中的任意点
But linked lists are also really good at pointing out at a very specific point or adding a new item in between two things.
但链表也确实擅长指向一个非常具体的点  或者在两件事之间添加一个新项目
So because of that, you end up seeing array-based options when you want to have constant time accesses.
因此  当你想要进行常数时间访问时  最终会看到基于数组的选项
And you will see linked list structures like trees or graphs when you want to have easy insertions of any arbitrary location in the list.
当你想要在列表中的任意位置轻松插入时  你会看到链表结构  例如树或图
So you had these trade-offs.
你必须进行权衡
And we saw a lot of data structures which had one advantage or another.
我们也见识了很多各有利弊的数据结构
At the very end, we also looked at a lot of these graph algorithms, topological sort, reachability, all of these different possible things.
最后  我们还研究了许多图算法  比如拓扑排序、可达性等等
Minimum spanning tree was a big one that we found.
最小生成树是我们发现的一个重要算法
And we showed that some of these were actually really easy to solve.
我们发现其中一些算法其实很容易解决
Some of these can be solved in polynomial time.
有些问题可以在多项式时间内解决
But some of these can't.
但也有些问题无法做到
Longest path, for example, is something that you just can't solve in polynomial time.
例如  最长路径问题就无法在多项式时间内解决
And we kind of discussed that briefly in our P versus NP lecture.
我们在 P 与 NP 那节课中简要讨论过这个问题
Other than that, we saw these search operations.
除此之外  我们还学习了搜索操作
For example, we had two, three trees, red, black trees as options to store binary trees.
例如  我们有二叉树、三叉树、红黑树等存储二叉树的选项
Those get rid of our theta and worst case bound and make sure everything is theta log n. And that lets us have practical sets and mapped operations.
这些结构消除了我们在最坏情况下的 Θ 界限  并确保所有操作都是 Θ(log N)  这使得我们可以进行实际的集合和映射操作
We looked at comparison-based sorts.
我们研究了基于比较的排序算法
We looked at, actually, a lot of different sorting algorithms.
实际上  我们研究了许多不同的排序算法
Comparison sorts was just the first one we looked at.
基于比较的排序只是我们研究的第一种类型
And we saw that there were so many that had n log n bounds.
我们发现很多算法都有 N log N 的界限
And we actually proved that no matter how you create a sorting algorithm, as long as it's a comparison-based sort, it is guaranteed to have omega n log n, worst case, runtime.
我们实际上证明了  无论你如何创建排序算法  只要它是基于比较的排序  它在最坏情况下都保证具有 Ω(N log N) 的运行时间
We also looked at some cases that actually go beyond the n log n bound.
我们还研究了一些实际上超越了 N log N 界限的案例
So we get faster than n log n runtime by not using comparisons.
通过不使用比较  我们可以获得比 N log N 更快的运行时间
So those were our counting sorts, our LSD, MSD radix sorts.
例如计数排序、LSD 基数排序和 MSD 基数排序
Those can get theta and worst case bounds because they rely not on comparing things, but on actually the fact that we're using integers.
因为它们不依赖于比较  而是依赖于我们实际使用的是整数  所以它们可以得到Θ和最坏情况的界限
And integers have special properties that not all comparables have.
而整数具有一些特殊的性质  并非所有可比较对象都具备这些性质
And then finally, this week, we kind of covered a few fun topics.
最后  这周我们涵盖了一些有趣的话题
We talked a bit about compression and how you might be able to compress data in a zip file.
我们讨论了一些关于压缩的知识  以及如何在zip文件中压缩数据
And we talked about P equals MP, or P versus MP, the big problem that we have for CS in general.
我们还讨论了P等于NP  或者说P与NP的关系  这是我们在计算机科学领域面临的一个重大问题
P versus MP is considered one of the most important problems that we have nowadays.
P与NP被认为是我们当今面临的最重要的问题之一
Even though most people believe P is not equal to MP, it's really interesting that we might be able to solve this.
尽管大多数人认为P≠NP  但我们有可能解决这个问题  这很有意思
And we talked about how if you managed to solve it, you win a million dollars.
我们还讨论了如果你能解决这个问题  你就能赢得一百万美元
Other than that, we also went a lot into the details, not just of concepts, but also a lot of practical, useful tools that you might see in real life.
除此之外  我们还深入探讨了许多细节  不仅是概念上的  还有很多你在现实生活中可能会看到的实用工具
A lot of this was about how you might become a better engineer, because we're not really teaching you how to program without telling you
这其中很多内容是关于如何成为一名更好的工程师  因为我们并不是在没有告诉你为什么要编程的情况下教你如何编程
Why you should be programming.
为什么要编程
Software engineering is all about those tiny things that you get as you develop your skills as programmers.
软件工程就是关于那些你在提升编程技能的过程中所获得的微小细节
So you need to know your ability to use Java syntax, idioms.
你需要了解你使用Java语法和习语的能力
Unit testing is critical for anything that doesn't have an autograder.
单元测试对于任何没有自动评分的东西都是至关重要的
Debugging, that's a really important skill.
调试  这是一项非常重要的技能
If you are going to office hours and asking for debugging help a lot,
如果你经常去办公时间寻求调试帮助
That's not as much personal debugging.
那就不是那么多的个人调试了
That's fine.
没关系
It takes a while to learn how to debug effectively.
学习如何有效地调试需要一段时间
But as you get better and better at programming, you should be trying to become more and more independent as a programmer and try to debug it.
但是随着你编程能力的提高  你应该努力成为一个越来越独立的程序员  并尝试调试它
Use some binary search tools.
用一些二分查找工具
Use an IDE.
使用 IDE
Use that debugging environment that goes step by step through your code.
使用可以逐步调试代码的调试环境
And make sure there's no place for that bug to hide.
确保 bug 无处可藏
We talked about tactical versus strategic programming, how sometimes when you're making a program that's really fast, you're going to write a program that's not really easy to change or modify.
我们讨论了战术编程与战略编程  有时候当你编写一个速度非常快的程序时  它可能难以更改或修改
You're not going to be able to use it for a long time.
你将无法长期使用它
So you want to try to have these strategic programming tools where you decide beforehand what your plan is for the entire project, and then you build based on that plan.
因此  你应该尝试使用战略性编程工具  预先决定整个项目的计划  然后根据该计划构建
And the downside is, generally speaking, when you think that something is just a proof of concept that will never be used in real life, that is exactly what guarantees that it will be used in real life.
缺点是  一般来说  当你认为某件事只是一个概念验证  永远不会在现实生活中使用时  这恰恰保证了它将在现实生活中被使用
So in general, it's a good idea to always assume that your code is going to be used in the future forever.
总的来说  始终假设你的代码将来会永远被使用是一个好主意
And you should be making sure your code is easy to change for that.
你应该确保你的代码易于为此进行更改
We actually use a lot of tools that get used in real life.
我们实际上使用了许多在现实生活中使用的工具
So IntelliJ, Git, the Truth library, the command line interface, all of those get used in practical programming environments.
所以 IntelliJ、Git、Truth 库、命令行界面  所有这些都在实际的编程环境中使用
You'll be seeing that if you take any internship over the summer.
如果你在夏天参加任何实习  你就会看到这一点
You'll be seeing that if you take any classes in the future that involve any CS.
如果你将来参加任何涉及 CS 的课程  你也会看到这一点
Git is especially very popular with pretty much all of the upper division courses.
Git 在几乎所有高年级课程中都非常受欢迎
And then finally, we discussed some algorithm design, how you might choose what data structures you use based on the problem you're facing.
最后  我们讨论了一些算法设计  你可能会根据面临的问题选择使用哪些数据结构
Sometimes you might see a problem and you think a naive solution that works in n squared time.
有时你可能会看到一个问题  并认为一个朴素的解决方案可以在 N² 时间内解决
But if you think a bit further, then you might be able to get an n log n or even n time solution.
但如果你再想一想  你可能会得到一个 N log N 甚至 N 时间的解决方案
And that will always be much faster than any n squared solution could ever be.
这将始终比任何 N² 解决方案快得多
So being able to develop those new algorithms is part of this algorithm design segment.
因此  能够开发这些新算法是算法设计部分的一部分
Does anyone have any questions about what we did over the entire semester?
这学期学的内容  大家有什么问题吗？
All right.
So I like to take this last lecture and just briefly talk about what you might be doing next semester, right?
那我想利用最后一节课  简单地聊聊下学期你们可能会做些什么  对吧？
That's probably the most important thing on everyone's minds besides the finals coming up.
除了即将到来的期末考试  这可能是大家最关心的事情了
What are you going to do next year?
明年你们打算做什么？
So personally, I think about these two questions as the two immediate things you should be looking at.
就我个人而言  我认为这两个问题是你们应该立即考虑的
What classes should I take next semester?
下学期我应该选哪些课？
And how should I prepare for the final?
我应该如何准备期末考试？
And you have also, I would suggest that you look not just at these two things that are for the new future, but also to long-term questions.
我还建议你们不仅要着眼于这两个近期目标  还要考虑一些长期问题
What are you capable of doing in life?
你在生活中能做些什么？
And what do you think you should be doing overall?
你认为你应该做什么？
Once you get out of here, once you become an actual software engineer, what do you actually want to do?
一旦你离开这里  一旦你成为一名真正的软件工程师  你到底想做什么？
So before I get started, I'd like to ask this question.
在开始之前  我想问一个问题
How many students are happy with the grade they're on track to receive?
有多少学生对他们即将获得的成绩感到满意？
A few students.
有几个学生
How many people are unhappy with that grade?
有多少人对这个成绩不满意？
A few people.
几个人
Why are you unhappy?
为什么不满意？
Or why are you happy or unhappy with the grade you're about to get?
或者说  你为什么对即将获得的成绩感到满意或不满意？
Any suggestions?
有什么建议吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
It aligns with what you expect for yourself.
这与你对自己的期望一致
Yeah, that's a really good reason.
对  这是个很好的理由
You expect yourself to get good grades.
你期望自己能取得好成绩
If you are on track for a good grade or a grade that you consider yourself capable of doing, then that's a really good feeling.
如果你正朝着一个好成绩或你认为自己有能力取得的成绩前进  那么这是一种非常好的感觉
And I suspect that if you're not happy with the grade you're on track to receive, it's also kind of that.
我猜  如果你对将要获得的成绩不满意  那也是这种感觉
You expect yourself to do better than what you were able to do this semester.
你期望自己比这学期做得更好
That's perfectly fine.
这很好
My other question is, what does a good grade actually mean?
我的另一个问题是  好成绩到底意味着什么？
How does a good grade end up affecting your future?
好成绩最终会如何影响你的未来？
What do you think?
你觉得呢？
Does anyone have any suggestions of what a good grade in this class actually means for your future?
有没有人对这门课的好成绩对你未来的实际意义有什么建议？
Yeah?
嗯？
If you get a good grade, you understood the concepts in the class.
如果你取得了好成绩  就说明你理解了这门课的概念
Yes?
是吗？
That's a very good indicator of the grade that you get.
这是你获得好成绩的一个很好的指标
What else?
还有什么？
What actual practical benefit are you getting from that grade?
你从那个成绩中获得了什么实际的好处？
Yes?
是吗？
You understand how exams are trying to trick you.
你明白了考试是如何试图欺骗你的
I don't like that wording.
我不喜欢这种说法
I would like to say you can apply the concepts.
我想说的是  你可以应用这些概念
In this class, in new and innovative ways.
在这门课上  以新的和创新的方式应用
What else?
还有什么？
What actual practical benefit do you get?
你实际得到什么好处？
What does a grade that you get in this class mean for your future?
你在本课程中获得的成绩对你未来意味着什么？
Yeah?
嗯？
Good grade leads to becoming a TA.
好成绩可以让你成为助教
Yeah, that's a good one.
那是一个很好的结果
Yeah.
Lets you declare the major.
让你可以宣布专业
I think we've gotten rid of the GPA requirement, right?
我想我们已经取消了GPA要求  对吧？
Yeah.
Yeah, there's still a few people who are in the old times when we had a 3.3 GPA limit.
还有一些人停留在我们有3.3 GPA限制的旧时代
I think now we're trying to get rid of that because it's not a great indicator of student success, really.
我想现在我们正试图摆脱它  因为它并不是衡量学生是否成功的良好指标  真的
But I think maybe you still need to get a decent enough grade to count the class.
但我认为也许你仍然需要获得足够好的成绩才能算这门课的学分
Yeah?
嗯？
Proof of hard work.
努力学习的证明
OK.
Yeah, yeah.
是的  是的
Anything else?
还有吗？
Well, I think other than just being a TA, are there any chats that are?
除了做助教  还有没有别的？
Ah, bigger number on resume.
啊  让简历上的数字更大
Fine, different number on resume.
好吧  让简历上的数字更好看
Lisa becoming a TA, I would also say not just a TA, but also a job, tends to be what a lot of students think about.
丽莎做助教  我还要说  不仅是助教  还有工作  这往往是很多学生考虑的事情
Also maybe graduate school, if you're interested in thinking about that.
如果你有兴趣的话  也可以考虑读研究生
Are there any other answers what a good grade in this class would mean for you?
还有其他答案吗？在这门课上取得好成绩对你来说意味着什么？
Here's personally what I think.
我个人是这样认为的
First of all, a grade in this course is not a measure of your worth or your intelligence.
首先  这门课的成绩不能衡量你的价值或智力
That's simply not true.
这根本不是真的
You can get a good grade, you can get a bad grade, but still be a good person.
你可以取得好成绩  也可以取得坏成绩  但你仍然是一个好人
The grade you get is nothing to do with who you are.
你取得的成绩与你是谁无关
It also doesn't really have much to do with the amount of work you put into it.
它也与你付出的努力没有多大关系
Just sometimes you have put in a lot of work, but it doesn't pan out.
有时候你付出了很多努力  但却没有得到回报
That's perfectly fine.
这完全没问题
It happens.
这种情况时有发生
I would note that a lot of students do put in a lot of effort, but they don't have that enough time to work through it.
我注意到很多学生确实付出了很多努力  但他们没有足够的时间来完成
So it doesn't really affect, mean so much about who you are, more about what you decided to do this semester and whether or not it was beyond what you were actually able to do.
这并不能说明你是谁  更多的是说明你这个学期决定做什么  以及这是否超出了你实际的能力范围
Now, your grades could affect your future.
现在  你的成绩可能会影响你的未来
I think the most common thing that students think about is future job prospects or grad school.
我认为学生们最常考虑的是未来的工作前景或研究生院
I personally actually don't think that's a big issue.
我个人其实不觉得这是个大问题
GPA is indeed a factor, but it's generally not a big, important one for most grad schools or jobs.
GPA确实是一个因素  但对于大多数研究生院或工作来说  它通常不是一个重要的因素
Like once you get into industry, you don't really care about your GPA.
比如  一旦你进入行业  你就不太关心你的GPA了
That's just the foot in the door for that first job you get.
那只是你得到第一份工作的敲门砖
And pretty much any GPA you get, you're going to get someone who's willing to hire you, especially in CS or data science, where pretty much every single person who has the skills necessary is going to be in high demand.
几乎无论你的GPA是多少  你都能找到愿意雇佣你的人  尤其是在CS或数据科学领域  几乎每个拥有必要技能的人都将供不应求
To enter the CS major, there is some There is some people who are having that difficulty.
要进入CS专业  有些人遇到了困难
I will say that we are grateful that we no longer have that GPA requirement coming in soon.
我要说的是  我们很庆幸我们即将不再有GPA要求
Every single faculty member and lecturer I've talked to has hated the GPA requirement.
我交谈过的每一位教职员工和讲师都讨厌GPA要求
And it's been a long time coming that we finally managed to get rid of it.
我们终于设法摆脱它了  这已经很久了
Because it incentivizes the wrong type of person to get in.
因为它激励了错误类型的人加入
It incentivizes people to think just about their grade and not really about the learning that gets attained here.
它激励人们只考虑他们的成绩  而不真正考虑在这里获得的学习成果
Personally, I think that the most important thing that a grade tells you is actually what you should be doing next semester.
就我个人而言  我认为成绩最重要的一点是告诉你下学期应该做什么
Once you get into college, you're always choosing what you get to do and what you want to do over a semester.
一旦你进入大学  你总是在选择你在一学期内要做的事情和你想要做的事情
And that means that you're going to overload yourself at some point and take too many things than you're able to.
这意味着你将在某个时候超负荷  承担超出你能力范围的事情
You're going to bite off more than you can chew at some point.
你总会在某个时候贪多嚼不烂
I would argue that the grade that you get here tells you that you did bite off more than you can chew on some semester.
我认为你在这里得到的成绩告诉你  你在某个学期确实贪多嚼不烂
Generally speaking, you don't truly master these concepts until you take the next semester course.
一般来说  在你参加下学期的课程之前  你不会真正掌握这些概念
So I like to think about the grade as a way to tell you how difficult your next semester is going to be if you decide to take a similar level of course load than what you had right now.
我喜欢把成绩看作是一种方式  它可以告诉你如果你决定承担与现在类似的课程负荷  你的下学期将会有多难
So if I give you an A in this class, what I'm trying to say is that you mastered all the material in this class.
如果我在这门课上给你一个A  我想说的是你已经掌握了这门课的所有材料
And I have faith that you're actually going to do fairly well in any future class.
我相信你在以后的任何课程中都会表现得很好
So for this 61C, 170, those two classes tend to be the next class after 61B.
所以对于 61C 和 170 这两门课程  它们往往是 61B 之后的下一门课
I feel like if you take those classes and you get an A in this class, you'll do fine.
我觉得如果你上这些课并且在这门课上拿到了 A  你会做得很好
You'll likely take less time than the expected, what is it, three hours per unit per week that you're expected to spend on that class.
你可能花费的时间会比预期少  也就是每周每单元预计花费的三个小时
So even if you have a ton of other stuff going on, you probably are going to be doing reasonably well.
即使你还有很多其他事情要做  你可能也会做得相当好
So you can take these harder courses.
你可以选修这些难度更大的课程
If you get a B, that generally means that you'll probably take about as much time as the average for those classes.
如果你得到 B  那通常意味着你可能花费的时间和这些课程的平均时间差不多
I'm saying that you probably comprehended as much about the material as the average student.
我说的是  你对材料的理解程度可能与普通学生一样
And that's perfectly fine.
这完全没问题
Most of these classes are designed to build from there, and you will have some reviews there.
这些课程中的大多数都是为了在此基础上进行构建的  你将在那里进行一些复习
So you'll be able to understand the material there, but you will have to develop based on that and develop new skills based on that.
你将能够理解那里的材料  但是你必须在此基础上发展并在此基础上发展新的技能
A C indicates that you are competent in the material here.
C 表示你能够胜任这里的材料
You understood enough of the material, but you'll probably struggle to develop beyond that.
你理解了足够的材料  但是你可能难以在此基础上发展
So you're probably going to end up needing to take more time in a future class than what we specify.
你最终可能需要在未来的课程中花费比我们指定的时间更多的时间
So if you're getting a lot of classes like 61C and 170, but you got a C and 61B,
如果你正在学习很多像 61C 和 170 这样的课程  但是你在 61B 中得到了 C
you might want to reduce the other workload that you're spending so that you have enough time to fully digest the material there and catch up to the B or A level.
你可能需要减少你花费的其他工作量  这样你就有足够的时间来充分消化那里的材料并赶上 B 或 A 的水平
Anything below a C generally means that you will struggle quite badly in another SQL course.
低于 C 的任何东西通常意味着你将在另一门 SQL 课程中苦苦挣扎
So going directly to that SQL course may not be the optimal strategy for you.
直接去上那门 SQL 课程可能不是你的最佳策略
It may be good to retake the course so you can kind of re-digest the topics, kind of understand what you missed.
重新学习这门课程可能是一个好主意  这样你就可以重新消化这些主题  了解你错过了什么
I kind of liken it to surfing.
我把它比作冲浪
When you're surfing, you have a bunch of waves.
当你冲浪时  你有很多波浪
And once you're behind a wave, it's very difficult to get back onto the top of it.
一旦落后于潮流  就很难再回到浪尖
But if you're ahead of that wave, it pushes you forward and makes it much easier to keep up to date.
但如果你走在潮流前面  它会推动你前进  让你更容易跟上时代
So sometimes if you're falling behind and you're trailing back, it's perfectly fine to wait a semester and come back for the next wave.
有时候  如果你落后了  完全可以等待一个学期  然后回来赶上下一波浪潮
That generally is going to be a better help for you, especially in terms of learning overall, than it is to just try to keep paddling and struggling and getting forward again.
总的来说  这对你更有帮助  尤其是在整体学习方面  而不是仅仅试图继续划桨、挣扎并再次前进
Back in spring 2016, Josh Hug, the previous instructor that ran this course, tried this experiment where he gave all students an option to fail the class intentionally.
回到 2016 年春季  Josh Hug  这门课程的前任讲师  做了一个实验  他让所有学生可以选择故意挂科
So if you were on track for a C, but you didn't want that C, you could opt to take an F instead.
如果你本来会得 C  但你不想要这个 C  你可以选择拿 F
And that would let you retake the course to try again the next semester.
这将让你可以在下个学期重修这门课程  再次尝试
On average, the students who did this ended up 2.5 letter graders higher than the previous time.
平均而言  这样做的学生最终比之前的成绩高 2.5 个等级
So someone in the middle of the B range would end up around an A level the second time.
因此  第二次  处于 B 范围中间的人最终会达到 A 的水平
So generally speaking, my interpretation of this is that even if you're not on pace for that grade that you want,
总的来说  我的理解是  即使你没有达到你想要的成绩
even if you are in that group of students who are not happy with the grade you have, you have still learned a lot of the material in this course.
即使你属于那些对自己的成绩不满意的学生群体  你仍然学到了很多这门课程的知识
That foundation is going to make it much easier if you decide that you want to take it again and relearn that course material at a later time.
如果你决定以后再学习这门课程的材料  这个基础会让你更容易
The bottom line here, even if you are struggling, even if you had so much work going on, you're capable of achieving much more than you think is possible.
底线是  即使你正在挣扎  即使你有很多工作要做  你也能取得比你想象的更多成就
Now, ultimately, 61A's main goal was kind of to just teach you how to program.
现在  最终  61A 的主要目标是教你如何编程
We didn't care about efficiency as much because we were just trying to get you to the point where you could actually write valid code.
我们不太关心效率  因为我们只是想让你达到能够实际编写有效代码的程度
61B's goal was mostly to teach you why you program.
61B 的目标主要是教你为什么要编程
So we gave you problems, and we kind of gave you an open space to do whatever you want with them.
我们给你问题  我们给你一个开放的空间  让你可以随心所欲地处理它们
Project 3 was a big one of those.
项目 3 就是其中一个重要的例子
You get basically nothing from us, and you get to build whatever you want.
你基本上什么也得不到  你可以随心所欲地构建
Because at this point, you are at the level where you can make whatever you want.
因为在这一点上  你已经达到了可以随心所欲地创造的水平
Your creativity is your limit there.
你的创造力就是你的极限
61C and 170 actually focus more on how to write code efficiently.
61C 和 170 其实更侧重于如何高效地编写代码
So 170 is focused on the theory side.
所以 170 侧重于理论方面
61C is actually focusing on the hardware and how a physical computer actually affects how you program effectively.
61C 则侧重于硬件以及物理计算机如何实际影响你有效编程的方式
So those are all about how you can make that code that you want to write and make it actually really efficient and actually feasible to run it within a reasonable time.
这些课程都是关于如何编写你想要的代码  并使其真正高效  并在合理的时间内实际运行
Once you get past the 61C170 level, you're generally going to be talking about very specific tiny facets of C of computer science.
一旦你过了 61C 和 170 这关  你通常会接触到计算机科学中非常具体的细微方面
So for example, CS161, that's a class all on computer security, how you make your code secure.
例如  CS161  这是一个关于计算机安全的课程  教你如何确保代码安全
CS162, it's all about operating systems, how your computer is actually able to run programs properly.
CS162  是关于操作系统的  关于你的计算机如何能够正确运行程序
At this point right now, you basically have enough understanding to build whatever program you want.
此时此刻  你基本上已经具备了构建任何你想要的程序的理解能力
Sure, it may not be as efficient as you want, and you might have to reinvent a ton of new things.
当然  它可能没有你想要的那么高效  你可能需要重新发明很多新东西
But generally speaking, you can do whatever you want with the coding knowledge that you have right now.
但总的来说  你现在拥有的编程知识可以让你做任何你想做的事
Ultimately, at this point, if you want to learn CS, then the best thing I can suggest for you is to just try building something new.
最终  在这一点上  如果你想学习计算机科学  那么我最好的建议就是尝试构建一些新的东西
Try it out, see what happens.
试试看  看看会发生什么
You're not going to succeed in most cases, but that's perfectly fine.
在大多数情况下  你不会成功  但这完全没问题
The learning process is by trying and failing over and over.
学习的过程就是不断地尝试和失败
So personally, I enjoy having fun with programming.
就我个人而言  我喜欢编程的乐趣
I consider programming to be not just work, but also a hobby of sorts.
我认为编程不仅仅是工作  也是一种爱好
And as it turns out, there's a lot of people who like the same way.
事实证明  有很多人也喜欢这样
And generally speaking, CS people tend to be good at making websites, and they like to share
总的来说  计算机科学的人往往擅长制作网站  他们喜欢与他人分享
Their passions with other people.
他们的热情
So there's a ton of these games that you can play around with.
所以有很多这样的游戏你可以玩玩
We talked a lot about them in Software Engineering 3.
在《软件工程 3》中我们已经详细讨论过这些内容了
All of these were covered at that point.
那时候已经涵盖了所有这些内容
But I would like to stress again, if you can, treat CS not as a job, but as a hobby.
但我还想再次强调  如果可以的话  不要把计算机科学当成一份工作  而要把它当成一种爱好
Find ways to play with the material and just kind of have fun with things.
寻找方法来玩转这些材料  享受其中的乐趣
Here are some video games that I personally recommend if you are enjoying this type of computer science themed games.
以下是我个人推荐的一些电子游戏  如果你喜欢这类计算机科学主题的游戏的话
Again, these were all talked about in our software engineering three as well.
同样  这些内容在我们的《软件工程 3》中也都讨论过
And if you want something more practical, you can attend some hackathons.
如果你想要一些更实际的东西  你可以参加一些黑客马拉松
The main reason why you're here at UC Berkeley, why we get a ton of similar like-minded students to the exact same room,
你在加州大学伯克利分校的主要原因  以及为什么我们让这么多志同道合的学生聚集在同一个房间里
is because you're going to be able to talk with new people.
是因为你将能够与新朋友交流
And those new people are going to come up with new solutions to strategies or new problems that no one's even thought about before.
而这些新朋友将提出解决策略的新方案  或者提出一些前所未有的新问题
Hackathons are kind of the distillation of that process.
黑客马拉松就是这个过程的提炼
In a hackathon, you basically just get locked in a room for an entire day.
在黑客马拉松中  你基本上就是把自己关在一个房间里一整天
You just build whatever you want.
你想做什么就做什么
It's a really amazing creative process.
这是一个非常棒的创作过程
If you can, I highly recommend doing at least one of these hackathons at some point during your career here.
如果可以的话  我强烈建议你在学习期间至少参加一次这样的黑客马拉松
So overall, for those long-term goals, what are you capable of achieving?
总的来说  对于那些长期目标  你能取得什么样的成就？
Pretty much anything.
几乎任何事情
As long as you have the time and the motivation to actually achieve what you want, you can do anything you want.
只要你有时间和动力去实现你想要的  你就可以做任何你想做的事情
What should you do with your life?
你应该如何度过你的人生？
Well, ultimately, it's up to you.
嗯  最终这取决于你自己
No matter what you do, no matter how well you do in these classes, or pretty much no matter how well you do in these classes, your skill set is going to be in high demand by everyone.
无论你做什么  无论你在这些课程中的表现如何  或者无论你在这些课程中的表现如何  你的技能都将受到每个人的高度需求
So your skills will enable you to do whatever you want in the world and affect it in really complex ways.
你的技能可以让你在世界上做任何你想做的事  并以非常复杂的方式影响它
As technology continues to shape our lives, it's up to you to decide how our future is going to work.
随着科技持续塑造我们的生活  未来如何运作取决于你
So you might look into all sorts of different problems that you have.
你可能会研究你遇到的各种问题
You might have intersection challenges.
你可能会遇到十字路口的挑战
Now that we have self-driving cars, do we really need red lights and green lights?
现在我们有了自动驾驶汽车  我们真的还需要红绿灯吗？
If everyone's all on the same network, then you might be able to control
如果每个人都在同一个网络上  那么你也许能够控制
Cars, so that all these cars can go in and out without actually relying on an intersection.
汽车  这样所有这些汽车都可以进出  而无需实际依赖十字路口
This is theoretically possible if all these white cars are coordinating together to ensure that there's no accidents.
从理论上讲  如果所有这些白色汽车都协同工作以确保没有事故  那么这是可能的
Other than that, you might decide to work for a tech company like Instagram.
除此之外  你可能会决定为像 Instagram 这样的科技公司工作
That is Instagram, right?
那是 Instagram  对吧？
Yeah.
是的
It's TikTok?
是 TikTok？
I'm sorry.
抱歉
Look, I somehow managed to miss the entire social media generation.
听着  我不知怎么设法错过了整个社交媒体时代
I'm sorry.
抱歉
Anyway, so TikTok over there.
总之  那边是 TikTok
Amazon.
亚马逊
Amazon's hiring a lot of people.
亚马逊正在招聘很多人
They're always looking for new software engineers.
他们一直在寻找新的软件工程师
You might be looking at solving some of life's bigger problems, like climate change.
你可能会着眼于解决一些生活中更大的问题  比如气候变化
You might be looking at teaching even.
你可能还会考虑去教书
I'd love to have all of you on core staff to help out TA.
我希望你们所有人都能加入核心团队  帮助助教
Both me and Perrin, we started off as students here.
我和Perrin都是从这里的学生开始的
We moved up the pipeline from AI to tutor to TA to head TA, and we eventually made it here up on stage.
我们从人工智能到导师  再到助教  再到首席助教  一步步走来  最终登上了这个舞台
What were you guys head TAs for?
你们当时是哪些课程的首席助教？
What were you head TAs for?
I was head TA for 61C.
我是61C的首席助教
Perrin?
Perrin呢？
161 and 61C.
161和61C
So you can do whatever you want.
你可以做任何你想做的事
All I ask is that I've given you these tools to change the world.
我给你们这些工具是为了改变世界
And all I ask is that you do what you think is good for the world.
我只希望你们做你们认为对世界有益的事情
You shouldn't work for low wages to uplift the downtrodden, right?
你不应该为了微薄的薪水去帮助那些受压迫的人  对吧？
That's a great thing.
那是一件很棒的事情
You can volunteer your life.
你可以志愿奉献你的生命
But you can make some money on the side.
但你也可以赚点外快
That's perfectly fine.
这完全没问题
But the main thing I want you to think is that if you're going to be working for something, make sure that what you do actually benefits the world in your interpretation.
但我想让你们思考的主要问题是  如果你要为某件事工作  请确保你所做的事情确实对这个世界有益
If you think that working for Google is going to be a bad idea because they're trying to steal all of our information and data and make us all addicted to our phones, then don't.
如果你认为为谷歌工作不是个好主意  因为他们试图窃取我们所有的信息和数据  让我们都沉迷于手机  那就不要去
Even if it pays a lot of money, you're going to be finding some other worthwhile cause that pays just as well.
即使它能带来很多钱  你也要找到其他一些有价值的事业  而且收入也一样高
If you feel like you're doing something good in the world, then that's all I care about.
如果你觉得你在做对世界有益的事情  那就够了  我别无所求
Even if other people think you're not doing something good for the world, as long as you personally believe that, I'm perfectly happy.
即使别人认为你做的事情对世界没什么益处  但只要你个人相信  我就很开心
Now, if you want to learn more about this, take CS 195.
如果你想了解更多  就去上 CS 195 这门课吧
That's a class all on the ethics of computer science.
这门课讲的是计算机科学的伦理道德
And it's a really good class to take and figure out what exactly our role as software engineers are in making this world a better place.
这是一门非常值得上的课  它能帮助你弄清楚作为软件工程师  我们在让这个世界变得更美好方面到底扮演着怎样的角色
So at this point, we've been talking at you for 40 lectures.
到目前为止  我们已经讲了 40 节课了
I think it's time that you get some chance to ask us any questions you want.
我想现在是时候让你们问一些想问的问题了
So yeah, does anyone have any questions for either me or Perrin?
那么  有人想问我或 Perrin 问题吗？
And Perrin, I am going to make you answer some questions this time.
Perrin  这次我要让你回答一些问题
Yes?
What would you recommend for a project over summer?
您推荐在暑假做什么项目？
That can go on a portfolio.
可以放在简历上的那种
I don't have any projects in mind, sorry.
抱歉  我没什么项目可以推荐
You can go first.
你先来吧
I really can't think of one, bro.
我真的想不出有什么项目  兄弟
Ultimately, I think it's just whatever you want to do.
说到底  我觉得你想做什么就做什么
I would point out that what you want to put in your portfolio is related to what you want your job to be in the future.
我想说的是  你想放在简历上的项目应该与你未来想做的工作相关
The job search isn't just companies trying to look for good candidates, but also candidates trying to look for good companies and good jobs that they want to actually focus on.
找工作不仅仅是公司在寻找合适的候选人  也是候选人在寻找合适的公司和他们真正想专注的工作
So if the project that you're working on is something that you're truly passionate in, then you're going to be specializing your resume for those companies that you actually want to work for.
如果你正在做的项目是你真正热爱的  那么你就是在为那些你真正想为之工作的公司量身定制你的简历
So my suggestion, really just come up with something new.
我的建议是  真的要拿出一些新的东西
Try to do whatever you actually want to do.
尽量去做你真正想做的事
Even if it's really ambitious, don't worry about it.
即使目标很宏伟  也不用担心
You can try it out.
你可以尝试一下
You'll learn something new even if you don't manage to complete it.
即使你没有完成它  你也会学到一些新东西
If you have questions, then feel free to come to my office hours.
如果你有问题  欢迎来我的办公时间
I'm happy to talk about new personal projects and what you might want to do with those.
我很乐意谈谈新的个人项目  以及你可能想用这些项目做什么
Yeah?
是吗？
We talked a bit about CTFs.
我们稍微谈了谈 CTF
What are they?
它们是什么？
Perrin, that is definitely you.
Perrin  那肯定是你
Well, I mean, I've never done one before.
嗯  我的意思是  我以前从来没有做过
I'm guessing you have.
我猜你做过
But yeah, it's like a, how do I describe it?
但是  它就像一个  我该如何描述它呢？
Like a security thing.
就像一个安全的东西
Yeah, well it stands for capture the flag, right?
它的意思是夺旗  对吧？
And it's a security-based thing where they give you a system that's vulnerable and you hack into it and score points for doing so.
这是一个基于安全的东西  他们给你一个易受攻击的系统  你侵入它并为此得分
That's my best understanding of it, but maybe you have a better picture of it.
这是我对它的最佳理解  但也许你对它有更好的了解
Yeah, yeah.
是的  是的
Capture the Flag is kind of this kind of game where you're given a system that's vulnerable to some attacks and you just try to break it.
夺旗是一种这样的游戏  你得到一个易受攻击的系统  然后你尝试去破解它
So you take someone else's code and you try to break it in new ways.
你拿别人的代码  尝试用新的方法破解它
It's actually really fun because you get to look at how the underlying code works and really look deeply into what's going on in order to actually find these breaks.
这其实很有趣  因为你可以查看底层代码是如何工作的  并深入了解到底发生了什么  以便真正找到这些漏洞
Are there any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Yeah.
有
Most of the CS department is on Mac or Linux.
大多数 CS 系的学生都用 Mac 或 Linux
What keeps me on Windows?
为什么我还在用 Windows？
Steam.
Steam
Actually, no, I personally just like the Windows interface.
其实不是  我个人就是喜欢 Windows 界面
I was raised on the Windows interface, and I generally tend to not like changing interfaces.
我是用 Windows 界面长大的  而且我一般不太喜欢更换界面
It is why I'm still using Microsoft Edge.
这就是为什么我还在用 Microsoft Edge
So, yeah, it's just my personal thing.
是的  这只是我的个人喜好
I don't like changes.
我不喜欢改变
I don't like making things different.
我不喜欢让事情变得不一样
Because it's the default and I am lazy.
因为它是默认的  而且我懒
Actually, Microsoft Edge uses Google Chrome now under the hood.
实际上  Microsoft Edge 现在底层使用的是 Google Chrome
And I used to use a Microsoft Edge version from before the Google Chrome change happened.
我以前用的是 Google Chrome 改版之前的 Microsoft Edge 版本
And it lasted until basically everything broke on that, which is like two years ago.
我一直用到它基本所有功能都坏了  那大概是两年前的事
Yeah.
What's the maximum number of upper division texts you should take at one time?
一个学期最多可以修多少门高年级课程？
I personally never took more than one upper division CS course per semester.
我个人每个学期最多只修一门高年级 CS 课程
I think there was one semester where I took two, and that was overloading already.
我记得有一个学期我修了两门  那已经算是超负荷了
That being said, I did my undergraduate as a math CS double.
话虽如此  我的本科是数学和计算机双专业
So generally speaking, I would do like one math class and one CS class at a time.
一般来说  我一次会上一门数学课和一门计算机课
And then towards the end of my school career, as I became more of a TA, I started splitting it into one semester of CS and one semester of math, doing one or two of these classes at a time.
然后在我学业生涯的后期  当我更多地担任助教时  我开始把它分成一个学期的计算机和一个学期的数学  一次上一两门这样的课
And I was still able to get both double majors and still able to have fun and take some classes that I just wanted to take.
我仍然能够获得双学位  仍然能够享受乐趣  并且能够选修一些我只想上的课程
So I would say don't worry about cramming in as much class coursework as possible.
所以我想说  不要担心尽可能多地塞进课程作业
You will have plenty of time to take all the classes you want to take over Berkeley.
你将有足够的时间在伯克利学习所有你想上的课程
Erin?
艾琳？
It's a good answer.
这是个好答案
I agree.
我同意
Do I like to read?
我喜欢读书吗？
I read sometimes.
我有时会读书
Books.
书
Come on!
拜托！
I haven't had a lot of time to read lately, though.
不过  我最近没有太多时间读书
All right.
Personally, I do read a lot, mostly Wikipedia pages nowadays.
就我个人而言  我确实读了很多书  现在主要是维基百科页面
Like, you know, when I get bored, I tend to look up Wikipedia pages and I tend to get bored when I'm eating and I tend to research the things that I'm most on my mind.
比如  你知道  当我感到无聊时  我倾向于查阅维基百科页面  而我吃饭时往往会感到无聊  我倾向于研究我脑子里最想的东西
So I now know a lot of recipes for some complete random reason.
我现在知道了很多完全随机原因的食谱
So I know all about like nixtamalization for corn and stuff.
我知道所有关于玉米碱化处理之类的东西
Yeah.
Sorry, I didn't quite hear you.
抱歉  我没听清
How do you find your niche in computer science?
在计算机科学领域  如何找到自己的方向？
OK, Perrin, you can definitely answer this one.
好的  佩林  这题你肯定能回答
I mean, I think Justin kind of covered it with just take a lot of classes, experiment with different things that you're interested in.
我觉得贾斯汀已经讲得差不多了  就是多上些课  多尝试自己感兴趣的东西
So for me, I had to try out research before I knew that it wasn't for me.
就我而言  我得先尝试做研究  才知道它不适合我
And I had to try out teaching before I knew it was for me.
我也得先尝试教学  才知道它适合我
So that's my short answer.
这就是我的简短回答
Do you have anything to add?
你还有什么要补充的吗？
No, not really.
不  没什么
Colleges is time for experimentation, you know.
大学是用来尝试的  你知道的
Do whatever you want.
想做什么就做什么
You have plenty of time to try and fail stuff.
你有充足的时间去尝试和失败
So, you know, don't worry about failures.
别担心失败
Just look for things that you find interesting.
只管寻找你感兴趣的东西
Yeah.
Any other?
还有其他问题吗？
Yeah.
有
You've heard that 188 is a bad class or is not a bad class?
你听说过188课不好  还是不坏？
So there's been some talk about 188 being a bad class.
关于188课不好  有一些议论
I don't think it's particularly a bad class.
我认为它不是一门特别差的课
It's just a class which looks different from what it actually appears.
这个课看上去跟实际上讲的内容不太一样
Actually, Perrin, you taught 188, so you should be the one.
Perrin  你之前教过188  所以应该你来讲
Yeah, I can take this one, actually.
好的  我可以讲这个
So yeah, I mean, I'd say 188, I mean, it's more like classical AI is what I would say.
我觉得188更像是经典的AI
AI is such a fast-moving field that things update every couple of years, and 188 hasn't really kept up with that.
AI 发展太快了  每隔几年就会更新  188 并没有跟上这个节奏
That said, when the folks designed 188 long before I got here, I've talked with them before, and I think the sense that we get is that they were trying to introduce concepts that are that
也就是说  很久以前设计 188 的人  我之前和他们聊过  我觉得他们是想介绍一些
they thought would always be timeless and they would always be around so I would say like it's not necessarily Cutting Edge
他们认为这些话题会永远是永恒的  它们会一直存在  所以我想说  这不一定是尖端技术
just because AI advances so fast and some of the topics are kind of left behind at this point
仅仅因为人工智能发展得如此之快  而一些话题在这一点上已经被抛在了后面
but I do think that some of the topics are pretty critical just in the sense that like they they will still come up in average AI discussions
但我确实认为  一些话题在某种意义上是非常关键的  就是它们仍然会在普通的人工智能讨论中出现
I'm not an AI researcher I can't tell you what isn't isn't relevant anymore but I think that's kind of the state of the class
我不是一个人工智能研究员  我不能告诉你什么是不再相关的  但我认为这就是这门课的状况
I mean there are also other restrictions like you know nowadays in AI neural networks are kind of the uh Hot Topic and they've enabled all this uh all the recent things that have been built
我的意思是  还有其他限制  你知道  现在在人工智能领域  神经网络是一个热门话题  它们已经实现了所有最近建立的东西
but at the same time neural networks require a lot of math as prerequisites
但与此同时  神经网络需要大量的数学作为先决条件
and 18a just doesn't have those so there are also bureaucratic obstacles
而18A课程中并没有这些内容  所以在让这门课程运转方面也存在一些官僚障碍
I think to making that class run but I do have thoughts on that so hit me up if you're interested
但我对此有一些想法  所以如果你感兴趣的话  就来找我吧
Yeah, I think pretty much, right?
是的  基本就是这样  对吧？
From my perspective, people go into 188 thinking this is a class on learning how to make ChatGPT.
我觉得大家选 188 是以为这门课教的是如何制作 ChatGPT
In reality, it's learning how to make the Pac-Man ghosts, AI.
但实际上  它教的是如何制作吃豆人里的幽灵 AI
It's still AI in a sense that you're telling a program how to behave, but it's not in, I'm going to let you come up with your own ways of behaving.
从某种意义上说  你是在告诉程序如何行动  这仍然是 AI  但它不是那种“我会让你自己想出行动方式”的 AI
Yeah, yes?
是的？
Yeah I mean I think we're trying to make little updates around the edges but ultimately there's going to be some bureaucratic roadblocks like
我们想做一些小的更新  但最终会遇到一些官僚障碍
for example there's only so much we can tell you if we don't expect linear algebra prerequisite because we don't so
例如  如果我们不要求线性代数作为先修课  我们就不能告诉你太多东西  因为我们没有
I would also say that classical AI is also much more relevant than you'd expect.
我还想说  经典 AI 实际上比你想象的要相关得多
In terms of how the Pac-Man ghosts work, I actually did look into that at some point.
关于吃豆人幽灵是如何工作的  我确实研究过
As it turns out, every single ghost has a different AI.
事实证明  每个幽灵都有不同的 AI
So Inky, the red one, I think always tries to target your location.
所以 Inky  红色的那个  总是试图瞄准你的位置
Blinky tries to get ahead of you.
Blinky 试图跑到你前面
Pinky tries to get ahead of you, but also randomly tries to run away from you over time.
Pinky 试图跑到你前面  但也会随机地试图逃离你
And Clyde just moves entirely randomly.
Clyde 的移动完全是随机的
So every single ghost got its own unique AI and own unique personality.
所以每个幽灵都有自己独特的 AI 和独特的个性
And it's really amazing that they were able to do that back in the Atari era.
令人惊叹的是  他们在 Atari 时代就能做到这一点
Yeah.
是啊
Someone on Zoom wants to know my favorite classes.
Zoom 上有人想知道我最喜欢的课程
And parents.
和父母
Like my mom or my dad?
像我妈妈还是我爸爸？
No, no, no.
不  不  不
My favorite parents.
我最喜欢的父母
No, no, no.
不  不  不
Oh, my parents' favorite classes.
哦  我父母最喜欢的课程
Okay.
I did not want to distinguish between my mom and dad.
我不想区分我的父母
All right.
So, personally, my favorite class.
就我个人而言  我最喜欢的课程
So, I went through Berkeley as a math CS double.
我在伯克利大学主修数学和计算机科学
So, my favorite class was honestly Math 191.
老实说  我最喜欢的课程是数学 191
It was a Putnam class, so there's this kind of yearly math competition for undergraduates where you get 12 questions.
这是一门普特南课程  所以每年都有一场针对本科生的数学竞赛  你会得到 12 道题  有 6 个小时来解决它们
You get six hours to solve them.
你有 6 个小时来解决它们
Each question is out of 10, so that's 120 points max.
每道题 10 分  所以总分是 120 分
And the average score is one.
平均分是 1 分
The median is one.
中位数是 1 分
It's a very difficult competition, but it's also really fun.
这是一场很难的比赛  但也很有趣
And what Math 191 was this preparation class to help you gain the skills necessary to do well in this competition.
数学 191 是为帮助你在这场比赛中取得好成绩而开设的准备课程  可以帮你掌握必要的技能
As it turns out, it's just a generally good proof writing class in general.
事实证明  它只是一门很好的证明写作课
So it was a really good class to take my first semester because that basically set the standard for me on how I can write proofs effectively in the future.
所以这门课对我第一学期来说真的很好  因为它基本上为我将来如何有效地写证明设定了标准
Other than that, CS161 was my best CS course, either that or 170.
除此之外  CS161 是我最好的 CS 课程  要么是它  要么是 170
Those were really fun for me, personally.
就我个人而言  这些课程真的很有趣
But that's because my style of programming is this kind of algorithm design, coming up with new things, finding ways to break things within the rules kind of thing.
但那是因为我的编程风格是这种算法设计  提出新东西  想办法在规则范围内打破常规
That's kind of how I think.
我就是这样思考的
Parran?
帕兰？
I also love math when I don't know.
我也不知道的时候我也喜欢数学
Just kidding, I never took it.
开玩笑的  我从来没学过
Or any semester.
或者任何学期都没学过
There's something else on Zoom.
Zoom 上还有别的事情
Answer what favorite classes you have.
回答一下你最喜欢的课程是什么
I don't know.
我不知道
I don't really have classes that I... People always ask me, like, what's your favorite class to teach or whatever.
我并没有真正喜欢的课程... 人们总是问我  比如  你最喜欢教什么课之类的
But I don't really have one.
但我并没有真正喜欢的
I think I just like us.
我觉得我还挺喜欢我们的
I like kind of being able to switch between classes.
我喜欢能够在不同课程之间切换的感觉
I like the diversity.
我喜欢这种多样性
Teaching one thing for, you know, like 15 semesters in a row can get tiring.
连续15个学期教同一门课会很累
So that'd be my answer.
这就是我的答案
All right, you said there was another Zoom question?
好的  你说还有一个 Zoom 问题？
Any other questions?
还有什么问题吗？
Yeah?
有吗？
What did I get on the Putnam?
我在 Putnam 考试中得了多少分？
My first semester or first year I took it, I got a 13.
我第一次参加考试时  得了13分
The second year, my sophomore year, I slept through it because it was in the middle of a 170 project and my solution required me to monitor the entire program as it ran over and over.
第二年  也就是我大二的时候  我睡着了  因为当时我正在做一个170项目  我的解决方案需要我监控整个程序的运行过程
So I ended up sleeping through the second one.
我最后错过了第二次考试
My third year, I think I got a 37.
我大三的时候  我想我得了37分
Which, yeah, so many of my friends got, like, 38s, and I was very annoyed.
我很多朋友都得了38分  这让我很恼火
Yeah, there was, like, I think a four-way tie for first in Berkeley, and all of them got 38 points, and I got a 37, so I was very unhappy.
是的  我想伯克利有四个人并列第一  他们都得了38分  而我只得了37分  所以我很不高兴
And I knew, like, three of those four people, so they, like... There's always someone better in your friend group, right?
而且我认识那四个人中的三个  所以他们……你的朋友圈里总有比你强的人  对吧？
Yeah.
是的
And then my senior year, that was the first year of COVID, which meant there was no, there was no Putnam.
然后我大四那年  是新冠疫情的第一年  这意味着没有 Putnam 考试了
Yeah.
是的
So yeah, my highest score was a 37.
我最高的分数是37分
Yeah.
All right.
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
All right.
So before we finish off this semester, I do want to note that we read all of the feedback, especially on these end-of-course evaluations.
在我们结束这学期之前  我想指出的是  我们阅读了所有反馈  尤其是这些课程结束时的评估
We are always striving to make ourselves better as lecturers, better as a class overall.
我们一直努力使自己成为更好的讲师  使整个班级变得更好
There is an official form that we get from the university and an internal survey from 6UMB that we'll send out ourselves.
有一个我们从大学得到的官方表格  还有一个我们自己会发出的61B内部调查
So you will have these two individual forms.
所以你将会有这两个单独的表格
I will note that these course evaluations, they factor quite heavily into our
我要指出的是  这些课程评估对我们的影响很大
So please let us know.
所以请让我们知道
Oftentimes a lot of students only mark like a five or a one depending on if they had a really good interaction or really bad interaction.
通常情况下  很多学生只会根据他们是否有过非常好的互动或非常糟糕的互动来打五分或一分
And that really skews the results because chances are there are a lot of students who just, there are a few students here and there that are upset with us
这确实会扭曲结果  因为很有可能有很多学生只是  这里和那里有一些学生对我们感到不满
because we have like these policies that we need to enforce with everyone.
因为我们有这样的政策  我们需要对每个人都执行
But yeah, please fill out these course evaluations.
但是  请填写这些课程评估
They really help both me and Perrin.
它们真的对我和Perrin都有帮助
Other than that, if you can, definitely go on to become teachers of your own.
除此之外  如果可以的话  一定要继续成为你自己的老师
We would love to have you as an academic intern.
我们很乐意让你成为一名学术实习生
In fact, I'm going to be teaching the AI academic intern class for next year.
事实上  我将在明年教授人工智能学术实习班
I'm saying it now.
我现在就说
I've told other students.
我已经告诉过其他学生了
It is a new class called CS 365.
这是一门名为CS 365的新课
If you want to AI for a class next year, then you will need to take 365 for that, assuming the department actually approves that.
如果你明年想在人工智能方面当助教  你需要选修365课程  前提是系里真的批准了
I think technically we're still waiting on official departmental approval or something.
我想从技术上讲  我们仍在等待系里正式批准之类的
But it should be fine.
不过应该没问题
I mean, it's practical.
我的意思是  这很实用
Huh?
啊？
If you already took 370, you probably don't need to take 365.
如果你已经修过370  你可能不需要修365
This is specifically for the academic interns, yeah.
这是专门针对学术实习生的  是的
But actually, I think if you already took 370, you may not even be allowed to academic intern, because I'm not entirely sure.
但实际上  我想如果你已经修过370  你可能甚至不被允许参加学术实习  因为我不完全确定
I think the union is trying to make it so that academic interning is mostly so that you can develop the skills necessary to teach.
我认为工会正试图让学术实习主要用于培养教学所需的技能
But by the time you've taken 370, you've already developed those skills necessary, so you should be looking for paid jobs like a tutor or a TA.
但当你修完370时  你已经掌握了必要的技能  所以你应该寻找像助教或TA这样的有偿工作
Yeah.
So I would note that as the years have gone by, the CS department has grown massively.
所以我想指出的是  随着时间的推移  计算机科学系已经发展壮大
And the only reason why we've been able to keep up with that is because we've been getting really strong teachers and TAs from the undergraduates to help out.
而我们之所以能够跟上这一发展  唯一的原因是我们从本科生中得到了非常优秀的教师和助教的帮助
As it turns out, like those undergraduate TAs, they tend to be on average better than the average graduate student TA, mostly
事实证明  像那些本科生助教  他们的平均水平往往比研究生助教要好
because these undergraduate TAs tend to be far more willing to put in the work, far more enthusiastic about teaching and the course material in general.
主要是因为这些本科生助教更愿意投入工作  对教学和课程内容总体上也更热情
So please come up, show us, join us in the fall.
请加入我们  在秋季展示自己  加入我们的行列
We would love to have you as part of our core staff.
我们很乐意让你成为我们核心员工的一员
Lastly, I do want to thank our current staff, all of the people who helped keep everything going.
最后  我要感谢我们现在的员工  所有帮助我们维持一切运转的人
Like me and Perrin, we're only two tiny cogs in the entire staff.
像我和Perrin  我们只是整个员工团队中两个微不足道的齿轮
We wouldn't be able to do anything without all of these TAs.
如果没有所有这些助教  我们什么都做不了
So please give a big round of applause for all of them.
请大家为他们热烈鼓掌
They are amazing staff.
这些教职工真厉害
Yeah.
So in finality, Perrin, do you have any last thoughts?
那么最后  Perrin  你还有什么想说的吗？
Can I go second?
我可以第二个说吗？
You want to go second?
你想第二个说？
Oh, OK.
哦  好的
So from my perspective, it's an amazing responsibility to decide how you want to spend these hundreds of hours that you'll be spending here at Berkeley.
在我看来  决定如何度过你在伯克利学习的这几百个小时是一项非常重要的责任
You have so many options.
你有很多选择
College is the time when you have the most freedom, but in some senses, the least responsibilities overall.
大学是你拥有最多自由  但在某种意义上  总体责任最少的时候
You have the most ability to choose what you want to do.
你拥有最多的选择权去做你想做的事情
And the choices that you make in these few years are going to shape your life in the future.
而你在這几年做出的选择  将塑造你未来的生活
Try and decide how you want to do that.
试着决定你想要怎么做
Take as much time as you want.
想用多久就用多久
Revell in this freedom that you have to do what you want and make your future life as best as possible.
尽情享受这种自由  做你想做的事  让你的未来生活尽可能美好
Don't worry about how others are doing.
别担心别人做得怎么样
Everyone has someone better that they know.
每个人都认识比自己更优秀的人
That's perfectly fine.
这很正常
The biggest thing you should be looking at is if you were a better person than who you were the day before.
你最应该关注的是  你是否比前一天的自己更好
And as long as you are seeing that improvement constantly or consistently, that's all really you need to be happy with yourself.
只要你看到自己一直在进步  或者说一直在变得更好  那就足够让你对自己感到满意了
You don't need to worry that you're not making it at the exact same pace as everyone else.
你不需要担心自己没有和其他人以同样的速度前进
As long as you are improving yourself, you will eventually do great things.
只要不断提升自己  最终你会成就大事
Personally, the reason why I'm here as a lecturer, it's not because of the pay.
就我个人而言  我在这里当讲师  不是为了薪水
It's terrible.
薪水很糟糕
Don't get me wrong.
别误会我的意思
I could make 50% more industry.
我去业界能多挣 50%
That's for sure true.
这绝对是真的
But honestly, I do this because I feel like this is the best place I could be.
但老实说  我这样做是因为我觉得这是我最好的归宿
This is the most good I can do for the world because I'm helping shape the future.
这是我对世界所能做的最大的贡献  因为我在帮助塑造未来
I'm hopeful that you, this entire class, will collectively do more good than I can do any one position.
我希望你们  整个班级  能够共同做出比我在任何一个职位上所能做的更多的好事
Please prove me right.
请证明我是对的
All right, there we go.
好了  就这样吧
Okay, well, it's 1.59, and, yes?
好的  现在是 1.59  是的？
Yeah, I'd like to give a reflection, but, yes.
是的  我想做个反思
Yeah, I'd like to give a reflection, but it's 1.59, and I tried this last semester,
我想做个反思  但是现在是 1.59  我上学期试过这样做
and I was contractually told that I couldn't say anything until 2 p.m., so that's what I'll do.
但根据合同规定  我不能在下午 2 点之前发表任何言论  所以我照做了
Do not redo that.
不要再做这种事了
Well, I'm not going to redo it, because that would be interesting, but I can tell you a little bit about what happened, in case anyone's curious,
好吧  我不会再这样做了  因为那会很有趣  但如果有人好奇的话  我可以告诉你们一点发生了什么
but it is 2 p.m., so class is officially over, so you can go if you'd like.
但现在是下午 2 点了  所以课程正式结束了  如果你们想走的话可以走了
You asked me to talk, so I'll talk.
你让我说话  我就说
That's OK.
没关系
Well, so for context, what happened last semester is that after the last lecture that I gave, I just came up and said something about my closing thoughts.
嗯  所以说背景  上学期发生的事情是  在我上次讲课结束后  我只是走上来随便说了些我的感想
So I wanted to tell you all about the importance of thinking about ethics in CS and talked a little bit about how we as college students, as a campus community, need to think about
我想告诉大家  在计算机科学中思考伦理的重要性  并稍微谈了谈我们作为大学生  作为一个校园社区  需要如何思考
You know, what we're here for.
我们来这里的目的  你们都知道
And so I kind of gave thoughts on that.
我之前对此发表过一些想法
It's on video.
有视频记录
I won't go over it again.
我就不再重复了
But basically, right after I did it, I got in some trouble.
但基本上  我发表完那些想法后  就惹上了一些麻烦
So I don't know how much of that I can talk about.
我不确定能说多少
But I was told by the campus administration that what I did wasn't appropriate, and I wasn't allowed to do it.
但校方告诉我  我的行为不妥  不允许我这样做
I was also told by just people sending me mail that I had no idea what I was talking about, that I was clueless.
还有人给我发邮件说  我根本不知道自己在说什么  说我毫无头绪
So I decided, you know what, I'll take some time, and I'll listen to people, I'll learn, I'll have conversations.
我想  好吧  我会花些时间倾听别人的意见  学习  并进行对话
And I figured maybe I'd come back and tell you a little bit about what I learned.
我想也许我会回来跟大家分享一下我的学习成果
So I guess that's what I'll do now.
我想这就是我现在要做的
But again, if you want to go, I don't take any offense, it's all good.
但再说一次  如果你想离开  我不会介意  没关系
And I will try not to waste too much of your time, because it's after two.
我会尽量不浪费大家太多时间  因为现在已经两点多了
But yeah, some of the things I learned in the past six months of just talking to people, having conversations, I learned that a lot of you kind of felt the same way, which is that
但在过去六个月里  我通过与人交谈、进行对话学到了一些东西  我发现你们中的很多人都有同样的感受
Thank you so much.
非常感谢
It's really a harrowing feeling to be like, we're all here learning.
我们都在这里学习  却感到这种痛苦  真是令人心碎
And meanwhile, like 30 feet from us, there's an active protest going on that's been going on for days.
同时  在我们不到30英尺的地方  一场持续了数天的抗议活动正在进行
So one thing I learned is that we're not alone in this.
我学到的一件事是  我们并不孤单
We're all in this together.
我们都在一起
Something else that I learned, having talked with other faculty who reached out, other students who reached out, organizers who reached out,
我从其他伸出援手的教职员工、学生和组织者那里学到的另一件事是
is that something that we don't do enough in this department, I think, is we don't talk about these issues enough.
我认为我们这个部门做得不够的一件事是  我们没有足够地讨论这些问题
For example, when I tried to say anything about it, I was immediately slapped with getting in trouble.
比如  当我尝试说出一些想法时  我立刻就被指责惹麻烦了
And by not talking about it, we also allowed other things to fester.
而且由于我们不去讨论它  我们也让其他事情恶化了
So for example, a couple months ago, another faculty member in one of the upper division courses posted something that was pretty blatantly misogynistic, in my opinion.
举个例子  几个月前  高年级课程中的一位教员发表了一些在我看来很明显的厌女言论
And it kind of opened up the question of, why don't we talk about these things?
这引发了一个问题  为什么我们不讨论这些事情？
And I remember seeing and reading a paper, to answer the question someone asked earlier about what are you reading,
我记得我看到并读过一篇论文  为了回答之前有人问到的“你在读什么”这个问题
I read a paper that said, well, one of the reasons why the diversity numbers in CS were so low and why
我读了一篇论文  其中提到  CS领域多样性数字如此之低的原因之一  以及为什么
We're struggling so much to keep underrepresented minorities in the department and onwards to graduation is because these are issues that we don't talk about.
我们如此努力地想要留住部门中代表性不足的少数群体  并让他们顺利毕业  是因为这些都是我们没有讨论的问题
So one thing that I learned and something that I hope that we can all apply is that sometimes we just have to talk about these things.
我学到的一件事  也是我希望我们都能应用的一件事  就是有时我们必须讨论这些事情
It's not that I need everyone to agree with what I'm saying, but I do think that having the conversations is really important.
我并不是需要每个人都同意我的观点  但我确实认为进行对话非常重要
I also learned, what did I learn?
我还学到了什么？
I did talk with other folks and they told me about how
我和其他人聊过  他们告诉我
Google is currently funding, to your point earlier, some billion-dollar contract with the Israeli government.
正如你之前提到的  谷歌目前正在资助一项与以色列政府签订的数十亿美元的合同
And they're providing cloud services, data compute services, for reasons that even the employees at Google don't really know about.
他们提供云服务、数据计算服务  其原因甚至连谷歌的员工都不清楚
They staged a protest pretty recently.
他们最近举行了一次抗议活动
A couple folks got fired from Google over it.
一些人因此被谷歌解雇了
So I learned that there are folks in our industry, in our community, who also care a lot about these issues.
我了解到  在我们这个行业  在我们这个社区  也有一些人非常关心这些问题
And are doing what they think is right, which I think is good.
并且正在做他们认为正确的事情  我认为这是好事
So that's something I learned about.
这就是我了解到的一些情况
I also learned about the University of California itself has investments in investment companies like BlackRock.
我还了解到  加州大学本身也投资了像贝莱德这样的投资公司
So some of my retirement fund is currently invested in firms like that.
我的一些退休基金目前投资于这样的公司
And they have ties to weapons companies like Boeing or Lockheed or other companies that
它们与波音、洛克希德等武器公司或其他公司有联系  这些公司
That are also supplying the bonds that not only are we funding with our university investments, but also the kind of companies that some of the folks that I imagine I'm teaching are going to go on to work for.
这些公司不仅获得了我们大学投资的资金支持  而且还发行债券  我猜想我教的一些学生将来会去这些公司工作
Those are all things that I learned.
这些都是我学到的东西
I don't know what to do with that information necessarily, but I wanted to share it with you and let you know that in response to folks saying it's not okay.
我不知道该怎么处理这些信息  但我想跟大家分享一下  让你们知道  对于那些说这样做不对的人
appropriate, these are the things that I learned.
不合适的人  这些都是我学到的东西
So if I were to do it again, I don't know that I would, or I guess, yeah, I don't know if I were to do it again.
如果让我再做一次  我不知道我会不会  或者说  我不知道如果让我再做一次
I don't know.
我不知道
I was told that it was inappropriate.
有人告诉我这样做不合适
And the more I think about it, the more I hear about conversations being so important to maintaining diversity and inclusion in CS, and the more I hear about the fact that a lot of us feel very alone and isolated,
我越想这件事  就越觉得对话对于维护计算机科学的多样性和包容性非常重要  而且我听到很多人感到非常孤独和孤立
especially folks from underrepresented minorities for whom this is like a living reality and not something that they can turn away from necessarily.
尤其是那些代表性不足的少数群体  对他们来说  这是一个活生生的现实  而不是他们可以轻易回避的东西
Really got me thinking about, is it really so inappropriate to talk about these things in class?
这真的让我开始思考  在课堂上谈论这些事情真的那么不合适吗？
Is it really the case that I have to wait until 2 p.m.
我真的要等到下午 2 点
after class is over to talk about any of this stuff?
下课后才能谈论这些事情吗？
I don't know the answer to some of these things, to be honest with you.
老实说  我也不知道这些问题的答案
I had a lot of second thoughts before I could even say anything, which is why it's kind of late in the semester.
在说任何话之前  我都想了很久  所以现在学期都快结束了
But I figured I'd share this with you just so that I'm still thinking about it.
但我想我还是跟大家分享一下  让你们知道我还在思考这个问题
I want you all to think about it.
我希望你们都能思考一下
Maybe we can have some conversations together.
也许我们可以一起讨论一下
If you want to, I can go stand outside for a little bit.
如果你们愿意  我可以到外面站一会儿
Maybe we can even walk over to Sproul and talk with some of the folks there if you want to have more conversations.
如果你们想多聊聊  我们甚至可以走到斯普劳尔广场  和那里的人聊聊
So yeah, I think that's kind of all I have, though.
我想这就是我要说的全部了
Just from me personally, I want to thank everyone for sticking around, being with us for 40-something lectures and sticking all the way to the end.
就我个人而言  我要感谢大家一直以来的陪伴  和我们一起度过了 40 多节课  一直坚持到最后
So.
Yeah, all solidarity with all the students who are outside, all solidarity with the folks who are still in Gaza.
嗯  声援所有在外的学生  声援仍然在加沙的人们
And I mean, as students, as educators, we're here in a university, and every university
我的意思是  作为学生  作为教育工作者  我们在这里  在一所大学里
and school in Gaza has been destroyed at this point, so they don't have an educational system.
而加沙的每一所大学和学校此时此刻都已被摧毁  所以他们没有教育体系
So all solidarity to those folks as well.
所以也声援那些人
So yeah, I think that's all I have.
嗯  我想这就是我要说的全部
I hope everyone has a good rest of their semester.
我希望大家在本学期的剩余时间里过得愉快
Free Palestine.
解放巴勒斯坦
Thanks.
谢谢